Guide to the Kingsley Association Records, 1894-1980 AIS.1970.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kingsley Association Records
1894-1980
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kingsley Association
AIS.1970.05
6.88 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
The Kingsley Association was formed in 1893 by George Hodges as a Pittsburgh settlement house. The collection includes: administrative and annual reports, books, brochures, budget information, case studies, clippings, correspondence, directories, minutes, photos and surveys spanning intermittent years from 1894-1980. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
History
The Kingsley Association was named in honor of Charles Kingsley, English Christian Socialist and author. The Association was formed in 1893 and was the result of efforts by Reverend Dr. George Hodges to establish a Pittsburgh settlement house on Penn Avenue. In 1901, house operations were transferred to a mansion purchased by industrialist Henry Clay Frick in the Lower Hill District at Fulton and Bedford Streets. In 1903, the Kingsley Association opened a "fresh air farm" at Valencia known as Lillian Home on land purchased by industrialist Charles L. Taylor, which remains in operation today. By 1919, the Hill District experienced an African-American population growth as a result of wartime labor needs; settlement house operations were the responsiblity of the American Baptist Association and became known as Morgan Memorial House. The results of a 1919 survey conducted by the University of Pittsburgh recommended that the Association relocate its settlement house to East Liberty where it continues to operate.
Scope and Content Notes
The materials include various administrative (annual) reports, brochures, budget information, by-laws, case studies, clippings, constitution, correspondence, directories, inventories, minutes, publications, scrapbooks, and surveys; dates range from 1894 to 1980 and are intermittent.
Series I contains the administrative records of the Kingsley Association. The registration books in Series II offer family information about the children (name, age, address, religious affiliation, ethnicity and parent occupations) served by the settlement house when it was located in the Lower Hill District.
Series III contains correspondence to Director Charles C. Cooper from Francis Tyson and J. K. Folsom. There are also photocopies of letters from Andrew Carnegie pledging support of the Kingsley Association. Series IV contains solicitations for funds and case studies.
Series V contains an undated speech by Judge Joseph Buffington regarding the Association's history of service and a draft of meeting proceedings held in conjunction with a reunion circa 1950. Series VI contains the 1919 University of Pittsburgh East Liberty Social Survey.
Series VII consists of publications, for example, brochures that feature the settlement house, Lillian Home and convalescent rest. The Kingsley Association annual reports offer organizational and procedural information about the settlement house and the Lillian home.
Series VIII contains scrapbooks of Kingsley House clippings, brochures and forms. There are also bound volumes of press clippings of various Kingsley Association activities from Pittsburgh newspapers, 1911-1949.
For more information on the Kingsley Association, see also: Thirty Years at Kingsley House, by Phillip Rosen (MPub 200), Study of Social Settlement Workers in Pittsburgh, 1893 to 1927, by Elizabeth A. Metzger (Mms 30), Neighborhood Centers Association (ais 64:28), African Service Institute (AIS.1963.01) and Eliot Papers (AIS.1969.02).
The Kingsley Association photographs span 1900-1970. Early 20th century photographs are a vital part of the collection which depict many views of the Hill District and East Liberty. Portraits include Thomas Bigelow, Joseph Guffey and H. J. Heinz; a signed engraving of John A. Brashear, and a signed print of Judge Joseph Buffington. An album of photographs were taken by Kingsley House Director, William H. Matthews. Photographs and depict various activities and construction at the Lillian Home and Kingsley House. There are also photo albums from various Lillian Taylor Camp outings in the 1940's and 1950's. Photographs are housed in the Media Collections at the Archives Service Center; a selection are available online at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/kingsley-association-records.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the Kingsley Association, East Liberty, in 1970 and 1980.
Existence and Location of Copies
Box 3, Folder 5, contains photocopies of correspondence from Andrew Carnegie; the originals have been retained by the Kingsley Association.
Digital reproductions of selected photographs are available at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/kingsley-association-records.
Previous Citation
Kingsley Association Records, 1894-1980, AIS.1970.05, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Kingsley Association, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1894-1980, ais 70:5, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Hill District (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Associations; Valencia (Pa.); Ethnic groups; Montooth Mansion (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Social action; Lillian Taylor Camp (Valencia, Pa.); Lillian Home (Valencia, Pa.); Social settlements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social surveys -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Ethnic groups -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Corporations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; East Liberty (Pittsburgh, Pa.); African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Carnegie, Andrew; Cooper, Charles C.; Kingsley, Charles; Hodges, George; Buffington, Joseph; Folsom, Joseph K. (Joseph Kirk); Kingsley Association; Matthews, William Henry
- Administration, I.
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1917, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees Minutes, 1894-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - President's Report, Minutes, Board of Managers, 1957, 1962-1972, (intermittent) (Box 1, Folder 2A)
  - Budgets, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Registration Books, II.
  - Girls served by the Kingsley House, 1912-1915 (Box 1, Volume 1-3)
  - Girls served by the Kingsley House, 1916-1919 (Box 2, Volume 4-5)
  - Boys served by the Kingsley House, 1911-1915 (Box 2, Volume 6-8)
  - Boys served by the Kingsley House, 1916-1919 (Box 3, Volume 9-11)
- Correspondence, III.
  - Charles C. Cooper, Director (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Andrew Carnegie (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Solicitations for Funds, IV.
  - Solicitations For Funds, Lillian Rest Stories (case studies) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters of Appeal, 1923-1946 (Box 4, Folder 7-23)
- Addresses and Proceedings, V.
  - Public Addresses - Judge Joseph Buffington speech, meeting proceedings (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Survey, VI.
  - East Liberty Social Survey, July-August 1919 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Publications, VII.
  - Annual Reports of the Kingsley Association, 1894-1903, 1905-1909, 1911-1919; [Removed and added to AIS Book Collection: HV4196.P6K52] (Box 4, Folder 26-28)
  - Annual Reports of the Kingsley Association, 1920-1940; [Removed and added to AIS Book Collection: HV4196.P6K52] (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Kingsley House Record, 1904-1951 (intermittent) (Box 5, Folder 30-33)
  - Kingsley House Stimulus, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Kingsley House Broadcaster, 1929-1931 (intermittent) (Box 5, Folder 35-37)
  - Brochures - Settlement house (1903-1980), Lillian Home (1921-1979), Convalescent rest (1927-1938) (Box 5, Folder 38-40)
  - Art and Music at Your Doorstep, February-March 1960 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Reverend Dr. George Hodges, The Settlement--Its Necessity (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Kingsley House and the Settlement Movement, Pittsburgh: Kingsley Association, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - William H. Matthews, The Meaning of the Social Settlement Movement, Pittsburgh: Kingsley House, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Charles C. Cooper, Settlement Finance, Boston: National Federation of Settlements, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Directory of the Philanthropic, Charitable, and Civic Agencies of the City of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh: Kingsley House, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Directory of the Philanthropic, Charitable, and Civic Agencies of the City of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Pittsburgh: Kingsley Association, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Directory of Settlements Affiliated with the National Federation of Settlements, January 1929 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Bibliography of Studies of Social Conditions in the Pittsburgh Area, 1920-1930, Pittsburgh: Bureau of Social Research, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Middle of a Century, Pittsburgh: Kingsley Association, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Kingsley Association, Pittsburgh: Kingsley Association, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - A Kingsley Portrait, 1893-1952, Pittsburgh: Kingsley Association (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - 75 Salutes for Kingsley, Peoples' Natural Gas Company, VOICE, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Renovation Study, Ross Association, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - The Kingsley Association, 1893-1968 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Press Clipping and Scrapbooks, VIII.
  - Scrapbooks, 1894-1916; 1.
    - Kingsley House Clippings, 1894-1907 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Kingsley House Brochures and Forms, 1911-1916 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Press Clippings, 1911-1980; 2.
    - 1911-1913 (Box 8, Volume 1-2)
    - 1913-1916 (Box 9, Volume 3-4)
    - 1916-1921 (Box 10, Volume 5-6)
    - 1923-1930 (Box 11, Volume 7)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 12, Volume 8)
    - 1939-1949 (Box 13, Volume 9)
    - 1951-1954, 1960-1980 (Box 13, Folder 58-60)
- Photographs, IX.
  - Photographs (Box 14, Folder 61-85)